A Finding Aid to the Irving and Hela Norman Papers, circa 1920-2010, in the Archives of American Art AAA.normirvi
Archives of American Art
Irving and Hela Norman papers
circa 1920-2010
AAA.normirvi
Archives of American Art
10 Linear feet
The papers of Irving and Hela Norman measure 10.0 linear feet and date from circa 1920 to 2010. The papers document the career of painter Irving Norman through biographical material; correspondence with family, friends, curators, art galleries, and museums; writings, exhibition records, personal business records, printed material, personal photographs, and photographs of his artwork. Also found are numerous audio and video interviews of Irving and Hela Norman.
Norman, Hela
Norman, Irving, 1906-1989
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Irving and Hela Norman measure 10.0 linear feet and date from circa 1920 to 2010. The papers document the career of painter Irving Norman through biographical material; correspondence with family, friends, curators, art galleries, and museums; writings, exhibition records, personal business records, printed material, personal photographs, and photographs of his artwork. Also found are numerous audio and video interviews of Irving and Hela Norman.
Researchers should note that the collection primarily documents Irving Norman's late career and Hela Norman's work to manage the exhibition and sale of Irving's work after his death. Almost all of the Norman's drawings and personal records were lost in a house and studio fire in December 1988.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
A small amount of material was donated by Irving and Hela Norman in 1988-1989. The bulk of the collection was donated in 2011 by Hela Norman via Tom Von Tersch, Trustee.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Related Archival Materials note
Also in the Archives of American Art is a videorecording of an interview with Irving Norman, produced by Bay Area Video Coalition, Zeke Richardson and Larry Andrews, in cooperation with the Archives of American Art. The interview was conducted by Michael S. Bell, March 5, 1988.
Separated Materials note
Additional loaned material, including slides, photographs of artwork, and letters, was returned to Hela Norman in 1990 after microfilming. Loaned material is available on reel 4705 but is not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1929-2010 (0.4 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1951-2010 (3 linear feet; Box 1-4)
Series 3: Interviews, circa 1974-2008 (3 linear feet; Box 4-7)
Series 4: Writings, circa 1974-2010 (5 folders; Box 7)
Series 5: Exhibition Records, 1980-2008 (1 linear foot; Box 7-8)
Series 6: Personal Business Records, 1974-2010 (0.8 linear feet; Box 8-9)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1940s-2000s (0.3 linear feet; Box 9)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1920-2010 (1.4 linear feet; Box 9-10)
Biographical/Historical note
Irving Norman (1906-1989) was a social surrealist painter in San Francisco, Calif. He married Hela Bohlen (1927-2010) in 1955.
Norman was born Irving Noachowitz in Vilna, Russia in 1906. He emigrated to the United States in 1923 and worked in a barber shop in Monticello, New York. In 1934 he moved to Los Angeles and opened his own barber shop in Laguna Beach. A few years later he volunteered for service in the Abraham Lincoln battalion in Spain, and upon returning to California, he joined a life drawing group. He attended the California School of Fine Arts in San Francisco in 1940, studying with William Gaw and Spencer Macky, and in 1945 had his first major solo exhibition. At this time he also won the San Francisco Art Association's Albert Bender Memorial Prize. In 1946 he studied at the Art Students' League in New York and traveled to Mexico. He received much press when one of his paintings was removed from an exhibition at the M. H. de Young Memorial Museum for obscenity in 1950. Despite this setback, he continued to regularly exhibition his work over the next decade.
A renewed interest in Irving Norman's work occurred in the mid-1970s, at which time he exhibited many new paintings. During the 1980s he continued to exhibit his work and participated in several video interviews. In 1988 a storm caused a fire which destroyed his house and studio, including drawings and most personal papers. Irving Norman passed away at home in July 1989 and a memorial retrospective of his work was held at San Jose State University the following year. Hela Norman continued to manage the sale and exhibition of Irving's artwork until her death in 2010.
Interviews; Painters--California--San Francisco; Painting, Modern--20th century--California--San Francisco; Photographs; Sound recordings; Video recordings
- Biographical Material, 1929-2010; Series 1; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here is biographical material belonging to Irving and Hela Norman, including citizenship, marriage, and death records, wills, and identification documents. Also found are documents regarding Irving Norman's activities, such as drafts of a biographical chronology and related notes, records of his participation in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, and photocopies and correspondence regarding his FBI file. Also of note are some photocopies of early records and photographs which were sent to Hela from a family member.
  - Cemetery Records, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronology, 1995-2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronology of Works, circa 2007 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Citizenship Records, 1958; 1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Death Records, Irving Norman, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Death Certificate, Hela Norman, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Early Biographical Records and Photographs (Copies), 2005-2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - FBI File/ACLU, 1996-2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Identification and Membership Cards, circa 1968-2009 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Items Relating to Memorial, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Last Will and Testament of Irving Noachowitz (Norman), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Last Will and Testament of Hela Noachowitz (Norman), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lists of Collectors and Public Collections, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Marriage and Divorce Records, 1946; 1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "My Paintings, Notes, etc.", 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Passports, 1956; 1989-2009 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1988-2005 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Documents, circa 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1951-2010; Series 2; 3 Linear feet Box 1-4
  Most correspondence consists of letters between Hela Norman and others concerning the works of Irving Norman, and post-dates his death. Included is extensive correspondence from 1989, the year of his death. Correspondence is with curators, museums, galleries, art dealers, friends, and family. Of note is extensive correspondence with curators Michael Bell and Patricia Junker; and friends Daniel Gundlach, Jerry Freeman, Judith Freeman, and Martin Sosin. Additionally there are many letters from Irving Norman's daughter, Maxine Ferriera, some of which contain biographical information. Researchers should note that letters from the same individuals may be found within the alphabetical and chronological correspondence. Most of the correspondence dated before 1975 are photocopies.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged as 2 subseries.
  2.1: Alphabetical Correspondence, circa 1950s-2010
  2.2: Chronological Correspondence, 1951-2010
  - Alphabetical Correspondence, circa 1950s-2010; 2.1
    - Archives of American Art, 1988-2008 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Toni Ati, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Michael Bell, 1975; 1983-2008 (Box 1, Folder 21-31)
    - Jane Block, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Maria Brooks, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Thomas Burke, 2003-2007 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - John Butcher, 1988-2006 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - John Carr, 1985-2006 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Susan Carson, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Gregory Davis, circa 1987-2006 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Emily Duffy, 1995-1997; 2006 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Michael Duncan, 2000-2007 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Charles Eldredge, 1989-2006 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Larry Evans, 1986-2006 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Maxine Ferriera, 1974-2010 (Box 1, Folder 43-45)
    - Maxine Ferriera, 1974-2010 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Jerry Freeman and Daniel Gundlach, 1968-2008 (Box 2, Folder 3-9)
    - Judith Freeman, 1983-2007 (Box 2, Folder 10-17)
    - Tatyana Goldwyn, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Regina Greenberg (Low), circa 1950s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
    - Jan Holloway, circa 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Patricia Junker, 1996-2008 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
    - Juxtapoz Magazine, 1997-2003 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Mark Kaufman and Colleen Johnston, 1977-1988 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Laughing Squid (Scott Beale), 2002-2007 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Oscar Lemer, 1985-2010 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
    - Norman Levine, 1970-2004 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
    - Jim Lind, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Mary Lindheim, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Roberta Loach, 1975-2007 (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
    - National Museum of American Art, 1987-2002 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Neubert, George, 1984-1995 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Nevada Museum of Art, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Jerry and Lorraine Parnes, circa 1996 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Peninsula Museum of Art, 2004-2006 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Bob Pokorney, 1999-2004 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Hank Rosenthal, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - San Jose Museum of Art, 2003-2007 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1984-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Harvey Sherman, circa 1981-1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Scott Shields, 1996-2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Alonso Smith, circa 1985-2008 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - Martin and Doris Sosin, circa 1979-2006 (Box 3, Folder 7-11)
    - Wayman Spence, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Spencer Museum of Art, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Helma Zeuze, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1951-2010; 2.2
    - Correspondence, 1951-1956 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1979 (Box 3, Folder 17-21)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 25-29)
    - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 30-38)
    - Correspondence, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 39-40)
    - Correspondence, 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence, 1998-2010 (Box 4, Folder 5-11)
    - Correspondence, Undated and Unidentified, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Interviews, circa 1974-2008; Series 3; 3 Linear feet Box 4-7
  Found here are many audio and video recordings of interviews with Irving and Hela Norman. Interviews were conducted for television programs as well as documentary projects. Of note are extensive interviews conducted at the Norman's home by Daniel Gundlach, an interview conducted by Oscar Lemer after the Norman's house and studio fire, and recordings for the short documentary by Susan Friedman, "Irving Norman: To Whom it May Concern." In addition to the original videocassette or sound cassette recordings, most interviews include digital copies on CD or DVD, and were transcribed in 2008. Some interviews also include additional cassettes containing selected excerpts. Additional documentation regarding these interviews may be found within the correspondence in Series 2.
  - Interview by John Carr, San Jose State University, circa 1974; 1 Videocassettes (VHS); 1 Videodiscs (DVD) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Interview by Michael Bell, 1975; 5 Sound cassettes Includes transcript and interview report.; 4 Sound discs (CD) (Box 4, Folder 14-17)
  - Interview by Daniel Gundlach, Judith Freeman and Hela Norman, 1983 June 27; 6 Sound cassettes Includes transcript.; 5 Videodiscs (DVD); 3 Sound discs (CD); 3 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 18-25)
  - "Watching Slides" at Daniel Gundlach's Home and Interview by Daniel Gundlach, 1984 March 10; 1984 February; 3 Sound discs (CD); 3 Sound cassettes Includes transcripts. (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    Transcript only.
  - Irving Norman Slide Show "The Human Condition", 1984 May; 1984 February; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic); 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Interview by Daniel Gundlach for Gino Rodriguez, 1985 November 29; 3 Sound cassettes Includes transcript.; 1 Sound discs (CD) (Box 5, Folder 7-9)
  - "Irving Norman" by Alonso Smith, 1987; 1 Videocassettes (Betacam) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Irving Norman Slide Show "The Human Condition", 1987 December 4; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "The Human Condition" on KCSM TV, 1988 June 22; 2 Videocassettes (Betacam); 7 Videodiscs (DVD); 4 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 12-15)
  - "Art Notes" (KQED) Interview by John Rozak, 1988; 3 Videocassettes (VHS); 5 Videodiscs (DVD); 3 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
  - Interview by Dr. Oscar Lemer, 1988; 3 Sound cassettes Includes transcript.; 1 Sound discs (CD) (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - "After the Fire" Interview by Dr. Oscar Lemer, 1989 March 5; 4 Sound discs (CD); 7 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 6, Folder 8-11)
  - Interview of Henry Nachowitz by Robin Clapp, 1996 January 17 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Hela Norman First Interview by Susan Friedman, 1996 March; 1 Videocassettes (VHS); 1 Sound cassettes Contains "Susan's selections" of interview excerpts.; 1 Sound discs (CD) (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - "Irving Norman: To Whom it May Concern" by Susan Friedman, 1998; 3 Videodiscs (DVD); 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 6, Folder 14-16)
  - "Irving Norman: To Whom it May Concern" by Susan Friedman, Project File, 1996-2005 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - "Arts and Minds #63: The Art of Irving Norman", 2002 January 17; 1 Videodiscs (DVD); 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - "Irving Norman" Dub, 2002 April; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - "The Art of the Matter" Interview of Hela Norman by Eleanor Dickinson, 2006; 1 Videodiscs (DVD); 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - California Report Interview of Hela Norman, 2007 February 16; 1 Sound discs (CD) (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - "Susan's 32 Films", 2007; 1 Videodiscs (DVD) (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - "Ray's Music: Possible Music for Irving Norman DVD", 2008 June 20; 1 Sound discs (CD) (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - "Irving Norman" Window Dubs, undated; 6 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - "Irving Norman" Transfers from Originals, undated; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Duplicate Digital Audio Recordings, 2000s; 1 DVD-R disc (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Duplicate Digital Video Recordings, 2000s; 6 DVD-R discs (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Writings, circa 1974-2010; Series 4; 5 Folders Box 7
  The scattered writings found here include notes written by Hela Norman, a brief biography of Hela, and hand-written recollections of Irving Norman by his daughter, Maxine Ferriera. Also found are a few essays about Irving Norman's work.
  - Notes, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Maria Beeler, "From War to Gardens: A Biography of Hela Norman", 2000 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Maxine Ferriera, "Recollections of My Father", 2010 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Joseph M. Lugo, "A Poem to You/In Light of Your Vision", circa 1974 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Writings by Others, 1985-2007 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Exhibition Records, 1980-2008; Series 5; 1 Linear feet Box 7-8
  Exhibition records consist of files documenting several retrospective exhibitions of Irving Norman's work. These files may include correspondence, notes, press clippings, exhibition publications, price lists, loan forms, planning documents, and draft catalog essays. Also found is a chronological set of exhibition press compiled by Hela Norman.
  - "The Measure of All Things: Paintings by Irving Norman," M. H. deYoung Memorial Museum (July 3-October 6, 1996), circa 1995-2002 (Box 7, Folder 12-14)
  - "Irving Norman: Social Realist," Mary Porter Sesnon Art Gallery (January 9-February 23, 1996), 1995-1996 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Touring Exhibition, "Exhibits USA", 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - "The Art of War and Peace," American Visionary Art Museum (October 6, 2001-September 1, 2002), 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 17-20)
  - "On Being Human: The Social Surrealist Paintings of Irving Norman," Santa Monica College (October 5-November 1, 2002), 2000-2002 (Box 7, Folder 21-22)
  - "Prophecy: Healing Time" SomArts (August 2-25, 2007), circa 2007 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Touring Exhibition, "Dark Metropolis: Irving Norman's Social Surrealism", 2007 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Exhibitions at Nora Eccles Harrison Museum of Art, 2000-2007 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Exhibitions at Crocker Art Museum, circa 2001-2008 (Box 8, Folder 1-5)
  - Exhibition Press, 1980-1987 (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
  - Exhibition Press, 1995-1997 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Press, 2000-2004 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Press, 2005-2008 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
- Personal Business Records, 1974-2010; Series 6; 0.8 Linear feet Box 8-9
  Found here are personal business records, including lists of artworks and documents regarding artwork appraisal, conservation, gifts, and photography. Also found is a bound index to Irving Norman's artwork which includes notations on what was lost in the 1988 studio fire. Additionally there are book project documents for Dark Metropolis: Irving Norman's Social Surrealism (2006), published by Heyday Books. Business dealings with several art galleries include correspondence, consignment and sales records, printed material, and price lists.
  - Estate Planning Documents, 1990-2009 (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
  - Legal Documents, 2001-2007; 1974 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Artwork Appraisal, 2008 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Artwork Conservation, 1997; 2001 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Artwork Lists, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Index of Artwork, circa 1980s (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Photographing Artwork, circa 2005-2006 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Gift to Art Institute of Chicago, 2007-2008 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Gift to Crocer Art Museum, 2007-2008 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Gift to Vilna Gaon Jewish State Museum, circa 2007 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Sale to Oakland Museum of California, 2007-2008 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Shipping Receipts, circa 1974-1979; 2002 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Financial Documents, 1988-2001 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Editions Press, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Travel Itinerary, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Travel Documents, 1991-2001 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Heyday Book Project, 2003-2007; Includes 1 videodisc (DVD) (Box 8, Folder 29-30)
  - Golden Gate Galleries (Philip Lederer), 2007-2009 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Jan Holloway Gallery, 1988-2009 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Michael Rosenfeld Gallery, 2003-2010 (Box 9, Folder 4-6)
  - Simon Lowinsky Gallery, 2009; 1974-1983 (Box 9, Folder 7-9)
- Printed Material, 1940s-2000s; Series 7; 0.3 Linear feet Box 9
  The small amount of printed material in this collection includes news clipping about the Normans, a few announcements for exhibitions of Irving Norman's work, and blank notecards that he designed. Additional printed material can be found within the exhibition records in Series 5.
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1970s-2007 (Box 9, Folder 10-13)
  - News Clippings, 1940s-2000s (Box 9, Folder 14-16)
  - Currant Magazine, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Blank Notecards, circa 1974 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1995-2007 (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Photographs, circa 1920-2010; Series 8; 1.4 Linear feet Box 9-10
  Photographs depict Irving Norman as a young adult, later in life with his wife Hela, and posing with his paintings. Also found is one photograph of him with fellow artist Charles Ware. Additionally there are photographs of Irving Norman's funeral, and early family photographs. Color photographs of Norman's artwork provide a nearly complete inventory of his paintings and are arranged chronologically. Many of the photographs are labeled with title, date, and current owner. The last three folders of photographs in this series are only available digitally and do not include paper prints.
  - Photographs of Irving Norman, circa 1920-1950s (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Photographs of Irving and Hela Norman, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 21-23)
  - Photographs of Irving Norman Funeral, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Family Photographs, circa 1920-1970s (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous Personal Photographs, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Photographs of Artwork (1939-1946), circa 2000s (Box 9, Folder 27-30)
  - Photographs of Artwork (1947-1959), circa 2000s (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
  - Photographs of Artwork (1960-1988), circa 2000s (Box 10, Folder 5-8)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Digital Copies, 1998-2002; Includes 8 electronic discs (CD) and 1 hard drive (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Artwork, "Accidentals", 2000s (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Artwork, "Later Finds", 2000s; Includes 24 electronic discs (DVD) (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Crocker Tour and Pictures from Shows, 2000s; Includes 1 electronic disc (DVD) (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Jesse Bravo Photographs, 2000s; Includes 6 electronic discs (DVD) (Box 10, Folder 13)